# NIRANJAN SINGH SENIOR FRONTEND DEVELOPER

+91-9665937717

Linkedin

niranjans3142@gmail.com

Website

# SUMMARY

Frontend Engineer with 8 years of experience architecting and developing scalable web applications using HTML, CSS, React.js, Next.js, and micro-frontend with client-side (CSR) and server-side rendering (SSR). Contributed to hiring, mentoring, and conducting code reviews. Focused on performance optimization, including load time metrics, WCAG-compliant, SEO, web vitals, and development reliability through rigorous testing and debugging, root cause analyses, and fixes reducing downtime, identifying and eliminating redundant API services.

# SKILLS

## **Languages & Tools**

JavaScript, TypeScript, Java, HTML5, CSS, Git, GTM, Sentry, Webpack, Datadog, Jenkins, AWS

## Framework & Library

Next.js, React.js, Java Swing, Redux, Express, Formik, Jest, Selenium, Puppeteer, Hotjar, Bitmovin, JW Player, GMaps, Chart.js, MaterialUI, JWT, Iodash

#### **Architecture & Concepts**

Micro Frontend, Server-Side Rendering, Single Page Application, RESTful APIs, Web Accessibility, Web Performance Optimization, Data Structures and Algorithms, Object-Oriented Programming, CI/CD, Unit Testing, BDD Testing.

# **EDUCATION**

2012-2016

P.I.C.T, Pune UNIVERSITY
Bachelor of Engineering, Information Technology.

2009-2011

Army Public School, Pune Major Physics, Chemistry, Math

## **EXPERIENCE**

## Viu, Senior Software Engineer, Domain: OTT, Sep 2022- Present

- Optimized and maintained a high-traffic web application, supporting 5M+ monthly active browser users with AVOD(Advertisement) and SVOD(Subscription) plans.
- Deployed and maintained shift from a legacy monolith to a micro-frontend architecture using ReactJS SSR, reducing load time by 20% and improving metrics TTI to 1.2s across 5M+ users.
- Enhanced browser AVOD ad revenue through stream tracking and placement accuracy, helping to generate revenue of 15M HKD for browser users.
- Engineered features: OTP security, video player control, Datadog trace.
- Streamlined API and architecture documentation on Confluence, enhancing cross-team collaboration.
- Developed Google Ads tracing capabilities that streamlined ad performance analysis and boosted campaign.
- · Integrated GTM for analytics and Sentry for health and performance monitoring.
- · Analysed POC to optimize login iframe caching for Huawei devices, reducing load times significantly with CDN reconfiguration and TTL refresh.

#### Elixia Tech Solutions Ltd, Senior Software Engineer, Domain: Logistic, Apr 2021 - Jul 2022

- Architected and enabled end-to-end logistics management for loads and goods using micro-frontend architecture for India's biggest E-Commerce
  platform, like Flipkart, including authorization, pickup, and delivery workflows.
- Orchestrated building and support of a suite of Supply Chain platform, divided into 3 major modules Pre Transit, In Transit, & Post Transit, billed on clients' subscription submodules, like partner onboarding, tracking, fleet management, capacity optimiser, bidding, and billing.
- · Implemented Onboarding guides for developers using Storybook, helping quick familiarity with the product story.
- Led migration from manual deployments to setting up Jenkins CI/CD pipeline, improving integration cycle by 100%, cutting deployment time from manual efforts to under 15 mins, enabling faster release cycles and rollback.
- · Coded and delivered key frontend requirements during the company's successful 2022 seed funding for 2M.

### YourMechanic, Software Engineer, Domain: Automotive tech, May 2020 - Feb 2021

- Worked on ReactJS micro-frontend applications with Ruby on Rails MVC, delivering feature reviews, promotional tools, and returning customer checkout flows
- Led and supported returning customer quick checkout flows, resulting in a 5-15% increase in conversion rates and contributing to MRR growth.
- Used Hotjar to debug code anomalies for quick support and fixes.

#### Software Engineering / Independent Consultant (Freelance), Jan 2019 - Feb 2020

- Urban Circus: Engineered robust test suites using Puppeteer and Jest, validating Google Maps disruption data and slashing integration testing time by 100%, accelerating continuous deployment cycles, and reducing errors.
- Eventera: Developed and deployed client-facing live event streaming platform, integrating JW Player for seamless playback, helping to broadcast 300+
  podcast and live events.
- Symphony Fintech: Designed and implemented responsive, cross-browser UIs to enhance interactivity and accessibility for real-time stock market execution features, maintained Swagger documentation, and shortcut key functionality, planning to reach 2B+ market size.

#### Persistent Systems, Software Engineer, Domain: Services(HealthCare), Dec 2017 – Jan 2019

- Generated actionable insight reports in Excel and PDF for ThermoFisher, resulting in improved stakeholder engagement on visualizing protein anomalies from FASTA-compliant format generated from Chart is using Java Swing, Vue. is for ThermoFisher client.
- Improved testing efficiency by reducing manual effort by 100% with an automated Cucumber BDD test suite.